Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, we look at the
best ways to treat ADHD,
and we start by taking a close look
at the effects of artificial food colors
in children’s diets.
Nearly 50 years ago,
Cedars-Sinai Chief of Pediatrics
Ben Feingold,
published heresy,
suggesting that
artificial food colors
could induce
behavioral disturbances.
Dow Chemical disagreed,
as did Coca Cola,
as well as other players
within the trillion-dollar
processed food industry,
who were able to convince
the medical establishment
that it was all just one
elaborate placebo effect.
But the truth can only be buried
so long.
In 2004,
a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled
food challenge was published.
Hyperactivity in preschoolers
was significantly reduced
when artificial colorings
and the preservative
sodium benzoate
were eliminated
from their diets;
but hyperactivity
jumped back up
when the additives,
rather than a placebo,
were reintroduced
into their diets.
The researchers suggest
the benefit would accrue
for all children
if they didn't consume
artificial food colors
or benzoate preservatives.
Then another randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled
food challenge was published
in probably the most prestigious
medical journal in the world.
This time, researchers found
that artificial colors
and other food additives
in processed foods
appeared to exacerbate
hyperactive behaviors;
impulsivity, inattentiveness,
and overactivity,
among young children,
with more pronounced effects
in 3-year-olds
relative to 8-or 9-year-olds.
And indeed, a more recent
randomized controlled trial
in 8- or 9-year-olds
in Hong Kong
didn't observe
a significant effect.
The authors suggested
it may be
because older kids
may be less sensitive,
or the dose used
was too small
relative to what
the kids typically consumed.
But what happens in children
already diagnosed with ADHD
if you remove
artificial food colors?
In a meta-analysis
of randomized controlled trials
for dietary interventions
for ADHD,
excluding artificial food colors
from the diet
significantly improved behavior.
In this meta-analysis,
the data over here suggest
that food colors were harmful,
whether assessed by parents,
observers,
or attention tests,
compared to studies
showing the opposite.
You can actually see
the difference in brain waves
on EEG compared to placebo.
As I highlighted years ago,
the European Union
requires warning labels
of potential adverse effects
on activity and attention
in children.
However, although
the Food and Drug Administration
in the United States has banned
a few artificial colors
like Red Dye No.1,
Red Dye No. 2,
Red Dye No. 4
due to cancer concerns,
no warning labels are required,
and many artificial colors
still predominate
processed foods.
Among grocery store products
marketed to children,
about 40 percent contain
at least one artificial color.
In 2021,
a report from the California
Environmental Protection Agency
highlighted the potential
neurobehavioral effects
of artificial food dyes
in children.
The authors concluded
that although not all studies
implicated them,
the current medical literature
provides a substantial amount
of evidence
that consumption
of synthetic food dyes
is associated with adverse
neurobehavioral outcomes
in kids,
and the FDA's
Acceptable Daily Intake levels
may not adequately
protect children.
For years I've been concerned
that Red No. 3
still hasn't been banned
from food,
given that it was banned
more than 30 years ago
from inclusion in any products
that go on our skin
due to cancer risk.
Finally, in October 2023,
the California Food Safety Act
was signed,
banning Red Dye No. 3
from foods and drinks
sold throughout the state,
while consumer groups,
including the Center for Science
in the Public Interest,
continue to petition the FDA
for a national ban
to prohibit use
of this carcinogen.
And on January 15 2025,
35 years after it was
banned in cosmetics,
the FDA finally banned it
nationwide in food as of 2027
and in drugs as of 2028.
In our next story,
the benefits of exercise in
controlling ADHD symptoms.
Every year in the United States doctors
write 20 million prescriptions
for stimulants like
Ritalin to give to kids
for attention deficit
hyperactivity disorder,
and it goes up every year.
In fact, more than
any other drug class
another 0.8 million added every
year to that 20 million.
That's a lot of amphetamines
for a lot of kids.
These drugs are
thought to act by
increasing dopamine and norepinephrine
levels in the brain.
Guess what else can increase
dopamine and norepinephrine levels?
Exercise!
And it happens within minutes
of getting on a bike,
levels shoot up.
Medications take
an hour to work;
physical activity works
almost immediately.
But does it work for ADHD?
According to the latest review,
-there isn't a lot of
research out there-,
but the current evidence
suggests that
both acute and chronic physical activity
can mitigate ADHD symptoms.
So while "medications and exercise
with regard to ADHD"
"shows that they both work
to more adequately regulate"
"dopamine and norepinephrine
levels in the brain”,
some of the new long-acting
formulations of drugs
can work for up to 12 hours,
whereas the therapeutic
effect of exercise
may only last
an hour or so.
But, the drugs produce
unwanted side effects
and have the potential for abuse.
"Exercise has been
shown to be effective"
"in controlling ADHD symptoms and
has essentially no side effects".
Well, that's not really true.
It should be noted
that a major difference
in the 2 treatment
modalities is that
medications have a defined
effect on ADHD symptoms alone,
whereas exercise produces
physical, mental, and emotional
advantages that
are far reaching.
So, exercise does have side-effects,
but they're all good.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.